Robert Richenburg
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Robert Richenburg papers
circa 1910s-2008
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Richenburg, Robert
5.3 linear feet
The Robert Richenburg papers, circa 1910s-2008, measure 5.3 linear feet. Biographical material, correspondence, subject files, writings, sound and video recordings, printed material, and photographs document the professional career and personal life of the educator and New York School painter and sculptor best known for his Abstract Expressionist paintings.
Provenance
Donated in 2008 by Margaret Kerr, widow of Robert Richenburg, on behalf of herself and his son Ronald Richenburg.
Related Material
An oral history interview of Robert Richenburg was conducted by Dorothy Seckler for the Archives of American Art, circa 1968.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original material requires an appointment. Use of audiovisual material with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Biographical Note
Robert Bartlett Richenburg (1917-2006) was a painter and educator in New York City, Ithaca, New York, and East Hampton, New York.
At age 13, Bob Richenburg's artistic talent earned him a place in a daily class for Boston Public School students at the Museum of Fine Arts. Most classes focused on copying; of far greater benefit to the young art student was the opportunity to wander through the museum and look at art nearly every day of his high school career.
Richenburg's father was an architect who also ran a stained glass lampshade business; neither endeavor was profitable, so the family endured very hard times during the Depression. To help support the family, after school and on weekends, Bob delivered ice and coal with an older brother, a job he continued while attending night school courses in liberal arts at Boston University. He studied at George Washington University in Washington, DC, 1937-1939, often working as many as four part-time jobs to cover tuition and living expenses; during summers and school vacations, he returned to Boston to work with his brother. Due to his difficult financial situation, Richenburg's college career ended before he earned a degree.
After learning that the Corcoran School of Art charged no tuition, Richenburg returned to Washington in 1940 to study painting and sculpture. Although uninformed about the art world, he realized that New York was a better place for an aspiring artist. In 1941, he began studying with George Grosz and Reginald Marsh at the Art Students League. On his own, he studied materials and techniques and copied paintings at the Metropolitan Museum Art.
With war looming and the near certainty of being drafted, Robert Richenburg and Libby Chic Peltyn (always called Chic) married in November 1942; two weeks later, he entered the army. Richenburg spent three years in England and France as a combat engineer, transporting explosives and instructing troops in the demolition of mines and booby traps. In England, he managed a photo lab and taught drawing in the fine arts section of Shrivenham American University, a school run by the U. S. Army.
Once discharged, Richenburg returned to New York and took advantage of the G.I. Bill to continue studying painting (and for the subsistence allowance that provided modest support for his family - son Ronald was born in 1947). Richenburg studied at the Ozenfant School, 1947-1949, where he developed a life-long friendship with fellow student Ibram Lassaw.
He continued his art education with Hans Hofmann in New York and Provincetown, 1949-1951. During this period, Richenburg taught drawing, painting, and art history classes sponsored by the Extension Division of City College of New York and held at venues such as Brooklyn's Central YMCA, and branches of the New York Public Library. Richenburg quickly discovered that he liked teaching and enjoyed the students.
In 1951, Richenburg joined the Pratt Institute faculty and taught studio courses at night; soon, he was teaching full time during the day. Richenburg began to achieve recognition as the youngest of the Abstract Expressionists and by the early 1960s his career was well established. Tibor De Nagy Gallery in New York and Dwan Gallery in California represented Richenburg, and a number of paintings were sold to museums and private collectors. As Richenburg experimented with new ideas and materials, his work began changing. He was a popular instructor at Pratt with several promising students who also began experimenting. In 1964, when the unorthodox work of one student in particular caught the attention of Pratt administrators, Richenburg was asked to change his approach to teaching. This roused student protests, and press coverage focused on the specific situation and academic freedom in general. He chose to resign rather than alter his teaching philosophy.
Richenburg secured a position at Cornell University. The confluence of his absence from New York City and the ascendance of Pop Art were damaging, and his career was derailed when De Nagy and Dwan dropped him from their rosters a few years later. After it was clear that he would not secure tenure at Cornell, Richenburg returned to New York in 1967 and began teaching at Hunter College. Daily life in New York was harder than he remembered and, for him, the City had lost its allure.
When offered the chairmanship of the Ithaca College art department, the Richenburgs were delighted to return to tranquil Ithaca, New York. Chic died in 1977, and Bob remained at Ithaca College until retiring in 1983. In addition full-time teaching and handling administrative activities as department chairman, Richenburg made time to work in his studio practically every day. He created a large body of work in a wide variety of media and styles, moving on to new ideas and experiments after exhausting his possibilities or interest.
Beginning in 1949 with a loan exhibition organized by The Museum of Non-Objective Art, Richenburg participated in a wide range of group shows. His first solo exhibition was held in 1953 at the Hendler Gallery, Philadelphia. Over the years, he enjoyed other solo exhibitions at venues such as: David Findlay Jr. Fine Art, Dwan Gallery, Hansa Gallery, Ithaca College Museum of Art, McCormick Gallery, Rose Art Museum (Brandeis University), Santa Barbara Museum of Art, Sidney Mishkin Gallery (Baruch College), and Tibor De Nagy Gallery. In the 1960s and 1970s, Richenburg's work was seldom shown, but from the mid-1980s onward there has been renewed interest.
Richenburg's work is represented in the permanent collections of many museums including Hirshhorn Museum, Museum of Modern Art, Philadelphia Museum of Art, and Whitney Museum of American Art. In addition, his work was acquired by many highly regarded private collectors including Larry Aldrich, Walter P. Chrysler, Jr., Joseph H. Hirshhorn, J. Patrick Lannon, and James A. Michener.
Robert Richenburg and Margaret (Marggy) Kerr, a painter and sculptor living in Ithaca, were married in 1980. Ms. Kerr is known for "brick rugs" made from cut bricks forming designs for site specific sculpture and garden walks. Richenburg became close to his stepfamily of three children, Marggy's grandchildren and her mother. After he retired from Ithaca College, Bob and Marggy moved to Springs in East Hampton, New York.
Although Richenburg suffered from Parkinson's disease during the last six years of his life, he continued to work in his home studio until physically unable to produce art. He died on October 10, 2006.
Scope and Content Note
The Robert Richenburg papers, circa 1910s-2008, measure 5.3 linear feet. Biographical material, correspondence, subject files, writings, audio/visual recordings, printed material, and photographs document the professional career and personal life of the educator and New York School painter and sculptor best known for his Abstract Expressionist paintings.
Biographical material includes educational records from high school through his studies at the Ozenfant School of Fine Arts using G.I. benefits. Birth, marriage,and death certificates are also found, along with Richenburg family memorabilia.
Correspondence consists mostly of family letters, including some illustrated letters and many handmade cards featuring original artwork. Condolence letters addressed to Marggy Kerr are from friends, relatives, colleagues, neighbors, and acquaintances.
Subject files contain various combinations of correspondence, printed material, photographs, writings and notes relating to Richenburg's professional career and personal life. They document exhibitions, gallery representation, gifts of art work to museums and individuals, memberships, teaching activities, former students, friendships, and other aspects of his life. Files of significant interest are: The Club, Tina Dicky and Madeline Amgott, Former Students (particularly Raphael Montanez Ortiz), Bonnie L. Grad and Lynne Moulton, Hans Hofmann, Ibram Lassaw, Philip Pavia, Pratt Institute, Hilla Rebay and the Museum of Non-Objective Painting, Tibor De Nagy Gallery, and Veterans Administration.
Writings by Richenburg consist of notes, reviews, artist's statements, and the text of a speech. Also included are quotations compiled over the years by Marggy Kerr of Richenburg's comments on art and life. Among the writings by others are student papers, reviews, and poems.
Sound and visual recordings include interviews with Robert Richenburg, often conducted as research for exhibitions. Videocassettes document events such as panel discussions, and artist gatherings; a few were produced in conjunction with museum exhibitions. Also found are videotapes by video artist Raphael Montanez Ortiz, Richenburg's friend and former student; Ortiz also appears on the DVD of Richenburg's memorial service.
Printed material includes items that are specifically about Robert Richenburg as well as items that incidentally mention him. The majority consist of exhibition catalogs and announcements.
Photographs show art work by Richenburg, exhibition openings and other events, and a variety of people and places. Among the events recorded is the "Artists Roundtable on Art of the '50s." Moderated by Dore Ashton, the panel included Herman Cherry, Sidney Geist, Ibram Lassaw, Mercedes Matter, and David Slivka. There are photographs of Richenburg's boyhood home in Roslindale, MA, and his house in Ithaca, NY. He is pictured with others including family members, dealers, and curators. Of particular interest are photographs of Richenburg in Provincetown, MA, 1952-1953, with friends, including: Giorgio Cavallon, Franz Kline, Ibram and Ernestine Lassaw, and Philip and Marcia Pavia. World War II photographs consist of images of art work (not by Richenburg), Richenburg and other individuals taken in France and England; a number include views of Shrivenham American University.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 7 series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, circa 1910s-2006 (Box 1; 0.1 linear ft.)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1940-2007 (Box 1; 0.4 linear ft.)
Series 3: Subject Files, 1942-2008 (Boxes 1-3, OV 7; 2.25 linear ft.)
Series 4: Writings, circa 1950-2006 (Box 3; 0.1 linear ft.)
Series 5: Sound and Video Recordings, 1996-2006 (Boxes 3-4; 0.75 linear ft.)
Series 6: Printed Material, 1947-2008 (Boxes 4-5; 1.25 linear ft.)
Series 7: Photographs, circa 1923-2006 (Boxes 5-6; 0.45 linear ft.)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects:
Ashton, Dore; Cavallon, Giorgio, 1904-1989; Cherry, Herman; Geist, Sidney; Kline, Franz, 1910-1962; Lassaw, Ernestine; Lassaw, Ibram, 1913-2003; Matter, Mercedes; Pavia, Philip, 1915-2005; Slivka, David, 1913-; Ozenfant School of Fine Arts--Students
Subjects-Topical:
Abstract expressionism; Art--Study and teaching; Educators--New York (State)--East Hampton; New York school of art; Painters--New York (State)--East Hampton; Sculptors--New York (State)--East Hampton
Types of Materials:
Greeting cards; Illustrated letters; Interviews; Photographs; Sound recordings; Video recordings
Names:
Amgott, Madeline; Grad, Bonnie Lee, 1949-; Hofmann, Hans, 1880-1966; Lassaw, Ibram, 1913-2003; Moulton, Lynne; Ortiz, Rafael Montanez; Pavia, Philip, 1915-2005; Rebay, Hilla, 1890-1967; Pratt Institute; Club (New York, N.Y.); Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum; Tibor de Nagy Gallery; United States.--Veterans Administration
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Material, circa 1910s-2006, Series 1:; (Box 1; 0.1 linear ft.)
  Awards for athletic events consist of a certificate earned for performance in a track and field meet sponsored by the Boston City Schools, 1930, and three ribbons won at camp, 1934. Military service records are certificates of recognition from the White House and the Commonwealth of Massachusetts. Documents relating to his memorial service consist of notes and texts of remarks by Margaret Kerr, Ronald Richenburg, Blake Kerr, Alexandra Richenburg, dealer Thomas McCormick, and former student and friend Raphael Montanez Ortiz. The remarks of Ronald Richenburg summarize the artist's life from a personal perspective. Richenburg family memorabilia consists of a receipt from the Boston Art Glass Shade Co. run by his father, advertisements for the coal and ice delivery business and small grocery store run by brothers Fred and Bob Richenburg.
  Subject files (series 3) - specifically, those titled "Ozenfant School of Fine Arts," "U.S. Army, " and "Veterans Administration" - contain additional records concerning Richenburg's education and military service.
  - Awards for Athletic Events, 1930, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Birth Certificates of Robert Richenburg [copies] and Ronald Peltyn Richenburg, 1940-2005 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Curriculum Vitae, circa 1968-circa 1995 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Death Certificates of Libby Chic Peltyn Richenburg and Robert B. Richenburg, 1977, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Driver's License, International, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Educational Records, 1931-1950 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Marriage Certificate of Robert Bartlett Richenburg and Libby Chic Peltyn; Wedding Vows and Marriage Announcement of Robert Richenburg and Margaret Kerr, 1942, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Membership Cards, Artists Equity Association, 1947-1951) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Memorial Service, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Military Service, circa 1946 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Richenburg Family (Box 1)
    - Biographical Notes; Genealogical Research, circa 1980s-1990, (photocopies) (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Memorabilia, circa 1910s; 1935-1936, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Voter Registration Card, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1940-2007, Series 2:; (Box 1; 0.4 linear ft.)
  Some letters exchanged by Richenburg and his wife Marggy Kerr are illustrated. All of their cards are handmade and feature original art work - painted covers housing paper constructions by Bob, and drawings and collages by Marggy.
  Richenburg family correspondence consists of a letter from Robert to his father, one from his mother, and a birthday card from son Ronald. Kerr family correspondence, comprised of letters and cards to Richenburg from his stepchildren - Blake Kerr, Garry Kerr, Meg Kerr Paulsen - and their families. Also included are letters from Marggy's mother, Mrs. John C. Doorty, as well as some illustrated letters and handmade cards. Condolence letters from friends, relatives, colleagues, neighbors, and acquaintances are addressed to Marggy and family.
  The majority of Robert Richenburg's professional and personal correspondence is scattered throughout the subject files (series 3).
  - Robert Richenburg and Margaret Kerr (Box 1)
    - Bob to Marggy, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Bob to Marggy, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Marggy to Bob, 1991-1994, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Richenburg Family, 1940-2004 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Kerr Family, 1987-2006, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Condolence Letters, 2006, (5 folders) (Box 1, Folder 19-23)
  - Condolence Letters, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Subject Files, 1942-2008, Series 3:; (Boxes 1-3, OV 7; 2.25 linear ft.)
  File for The Club (The Artists' Club) includes two postcards announcing panel discussions (Robert Richenburg on the panel), 1951 and 1957, along with correspondence and e-mail regarding a documentary film about the Club. The Tina Dickey and Madeline Amgott file concerns their interview and videotape of Robert Richenburg, one of many former Hans Hofmann students contacted when the Metropolitan Museum of Art was organizing a Hans Hofmann exhibition; a transcript of their interview with Richenburg is included. Bonnie L. Grad and Lynne Moulton's research was conducted for the exhibition "Robert Richenburg: Abstract Expressionist" at Brandeis University's Rose Art Museum. Records preserved in this file include the transcript of a detailed interview with Richenburg about his early life, art training, and career; the transcript of a "slide discussion" in which the artist provided background information about each of the works being considered for inclusion in the exhibition. The file titled Former Students includes letters and printed material about the early career and personal life of Raphael Montanez Ortiz ("Bob's favorite student," according to Marggy). Hans Hoffman's file consists of letters of recommendation, brief letters and notes addressed to Bob and Chick (sic) from Miz and Hans Hofmann, a short statement by Richenburg about Hofmann as a teacher, and miscellaneous printed material. The subject file titled Ibram Lassaw contains "Artists of the New York School and Friends Celebrate the Eighty-first Birthday of Ibram Lassaw at an Informal Gathering and Discussion," a souvenir booklet of images by Cynthia Dantzic, 1994; also included are pages composed by Richenburg and Kerr for Lassaw's memorial book. Philip Pavia's file concerns the founding of It Is magazine. The Pratt Institute file includes correspondence and printed documentation concerning Richenburg's 1964 resignation from the faculty sparked by a dispute over his teaching methods. Hilla Rebay and the Museum of Non-Objective Painting file contains letters inviting Richenburg to participate in three exhibitions with an installation photograph showing Richenburg's three entries in the 1949 exhibition; other letters offer career advice, critiques, and modest grants for the purchase of art supplies. The Tibor De Nagy Gallery file includes a letter of advice from John Bernard Myers regarding "rhetoric surrounding the question of pricing," observations on how the size of a painting may affect its desirability and price, and the inadvisability of artists creating myths about themselves. The Veterans Administration subject file documents Richenburg's subsistence allowance and training benefits under the G.I. Bill, and a contract for Richenburg to study at the Ozenfant School, 1948-1949.
  Subject files for individuals are alphabetized by last name, all others are alphabetized by title.
  - Aldrich Museum, (See: box 2, folder 49) (Box 1)
  - American Academy of Arts and Letters, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - American Federation of Arts, 1960-1969 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Amgott, Madeline, (See: box 2, folders 8-9) (Box 1)
  - Anderson, Jeff, (See: box 2, folder 15) (Box 1)
  - Archives Requests (Archives of American Art; Syracuse University), 1964-1988 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Arlene Bujese Gallery, 1994-1999 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - "Art Beat" (television program), 1986 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - The Artists' Club, (See: The Club, box 1, folder 46) (Box 1)
  - Artists Equity Association, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - The Artists' Gallery, 1957, (Oversized material housed in OV 7) (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Ashton, Dore, 2001-2004 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Auctions, 1979-1992 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    Christie's
    First East End Art Auction for the Benefit of the Long Island Council on Alcoholism
    Friends of Pianofest
    Guernsey's
  - Baruch College, Sidney Mishkin Gallery, 1993-2008, (See also: box 1, folder 38) (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Benton Gallery, 1986-1993 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Bita, Lili, (See: box 3, folder 42) (Box 1)
  - Black Mirror, Missing Painting, 2000-2003 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Bologna/Landi Gallery, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Book, Robert Richenburg: The Richard Zahn Collection, 2006, (See also: box 1, folder 34; box 3, folder 24) (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Brandeis University, Rose Art Museum, 1992-2003, (See also: box 2, folders 24-28) (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Bryant, Edward and Tamara, 1960-1989 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Bujese, Arlene, (See: box 1, folder 28) (Box 1)
  - Castagna, Lawrence, Art Conservator, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Chrysler Art Museum of Provincetown, 1958-1962 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Chrysler Collection, 1957-1989 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Chrysler Museum, Norfolk, Va., 1980, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Church, Marilyn, (See: box 2, folder 15) (Box 1)
  - City College of New York, 1947-1950 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - The Club, 1951-2006 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Colgate University, Picker Gallery, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Collectors, 1962-2003, undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
    Tom and Darlene Furst
    Brent B. Johnson
    James E. Jordan
    Bob and Jane McSweeney
    David Pincus
    Alice and David Siegel
    Richard and Marcia Weisman
    Judy and Ed Weltman
  - Cooper Union, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Cornell Club Dinner, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Cornell College, Mount Vernon, Iowa, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Cornell University, (See also: box 2, folder 21) (Box 1)
    - Academic Appointment, 1964-1967, undated (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Exhibitions, 1964-1982 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Cotter, Norman M., 1965 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Coulbourn, Anne, (See: box 2, folder 15) (Box 1)
  - Creative Artists Public Service Program, 1971-1978 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - David Findlay Galleries Inc., 1978 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - David Findlay Jr. Fine Art (Box 2)
    - Group Show with Mike Kanemitsu and Fred Mitchell; "Robert Richenburg at 85," 2002-2003 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - "Robert Richenburg," 2003-2004 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - "Face to Face," 2004 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - "American Abstractionists"; "Robert Richenburg: Works on Paper from the 1940s," 2005 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - "Twelve New York Painters"; "Nine Artists from the Ninth Street Show," 2006 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Day, John, (See: box 2, folder 16) (Box 2)
  - Dayton Art Institute, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - De Nagy Gallery, (See: box 3, folder 31) (Box 2)
  - Dickey, Tina and Madeline Amgott (Box 2)
    - Correspondence regarding Richenburg Interview and Videotape about Hans Hofmann, 1998-2004 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Transcript of Videotaped Interview with Richenburg about Hans Hofmann (June 6), 1998 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Dickey, Tina - Transcript of Interview with Richenburg about Hans Hofmann (May 17), with revised versions, 1998-2000 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Dictionary of Contemporary American Artists, (See: Who's Who and Dictionary of Contemporary American Artists, box 3, folder 39) (Box 2)
  - Dine, Jim, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Dwan Gallery and Virginia Dwan, 1960-2006 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - East Remington Road, Ithaca, NY (Richenburg home), 1965-1985 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Everson Museum of Art, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Findlay, David, (See: box 2, folder 1) (Box 2)
  - Findlay, David, Jr., (See: box 2, folders 2-6) (Box 2)
  - Former Students (Box 2)
    - Anderson, Jeff - Coulbourn, Anne, 1976-2000, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
      Anderson, Jeff
      Church, Marilyn
      Coulbourn, Anne
    - Day, John 1995-2008, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Koren, Ed - Moskowitz, Robert, 1980-2006, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
      Koren, Ed
      La Noue, Terrence
      Maffia, Donald
      Moskowitz, Robert
    - Ortiz, Raphael Montanez, 1970-2007, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)